

Muhammad Haseeb Tariq

Data Scientist

mhaseebtariq@gmail.com



[Request on LinkedIn]



Utrecht, The Netherlands



https://mhaseebtariq.com



https://github.com/mhaseebtariq



https://nl.linkedin.com/in/muhammad-haseeb-tariq-3b817260



ABOUT

I believe I have the ideal mix of skills when it comes to the applied and practical sides of data science. With over 12 years of professional experience I have been a part of many successful data initiatives (and projects), but more importantly I have also had my fair share of failures. Those failures have helped me greatly in becoming a strategic thinker. I attribute the success of my career to the following two aspects:

- 1. Consciously striving to surround myself with people who are smarter than me
- 2. Getting things done despite the most unfavorable circumstances

I am currently leading the data science efforts at BrandLoyalty. I am helping BrandLoyalty set up the department of "Decision Intelligence". My main focus, thus far, has been on optimizing the operational forecasts (/decisions) with in the organization.



WORK EXPERIENCE

Lead Data Scientist, BrandLoyalty

Feb 2019 - Present

BrandLoyalty designs, develops and implements loyalty solutions that help the world's most successful retailers to change consumers' behaviour. Some of my major responsibilities and projects include:

- Exploring and prioritizing use cases
- o Leading the data science adoption efforts and setting the strategic vision
- Hiring, training, and mentoring team members
- Program impact analysis using timeseries modeling
- RAVEN [Ratios and Volume Excellence]: A unique (demand forecasting) model implementation, combining the concepts of (both) Boosting and Bagging
- [Early phase] A predictive model for pre-empting redemptions

Senior Data Scientist. Coolblue

Feb 2016 - Feb 2019 **③** 3 years

Coolblue is one of the largest online shops in the Benelux region. Some of my major responsibilities and projects included:

- GFM [Generalised Forecasting Machine]: A fully automated timeseries modeling engine for operational forecasting
- A recommender system that predicts the ideal sequence of pages, given the most recent (page) clicks of a user
- Google Adwords bidding schedule optimiser

- o Early phase models: Pricing optimisation, email pressure, and fraud detection
- o Training and mentoring the junior team members
- o Assisting the hiring manager in the recruitment process

Data Scientist, Convo

Jun 2014 - Nov 2015 **O** 1 year 6 months

Convo is a work collaboration platform that goes beyond chat/messenger solutions. My major responsibilities and projects included:

- Utilizing data science to improve the overall user retention rate
- Exploratory analyses for understanding user behaviour and trends
- o Implemented a customer churn model for improving the user onboarding wizard

Data Analyst / BI Engineer, Pring

Pring was one of the biggest micro-blogging services from Pakistan. Some of my major responsibilities and projects included:

- o Developed an NLP model for extracting and matching (pre-selected) topics
- o Extensively developed monitoring and reporting tools for Pring
- o Lead and managed the side-projects for company's internship program
- o During the earlier period of Pring, I also gained extensive experience in software/data engineering
 - ... [omitting those projects because of irrelevancy]



SKILLS

Programming: Python, R, Tensorflow, R Shiny, Django, Flask, JavaScript, D3.js, OOP, RESTful API Design

Databases: MySQL, MSSQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, MongoDB, Cassandra, Redis

Cloud / Distributed Computing: AWS, GCP, Azure, Spark, Hadoop

MLOps: Unix-like operating systems, Docker, TeamCity, Apache Airflow



EDUCATION

MSc in Advanced Computer Science (Data Science), University of Manchester, UK

2013 - 2014

BSc (Hons) in Computer Science, NCBA&E Lahore, Pakistan

2004 - 2008



INTERESTS

Sports

Squash

Cricket

Cooking



LANGUAGES